<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resume>
  <personal>
    <name>Dinesh Chhantyal</name>
    <location>New York, NY</location>
    <phone>+1-318-750-6383</phone>
    <email>myagdichhantyal@gmail.com</email>
    <website>https://www.dineshchhantyal.com</website>
    <linkedin>https://linkedin.com/in/dineshchhantyal</linkedin>
    <github>https://github.com/dineshchhantyal</github>
  </personal>

  <summary>
    Dedicated Computer Science student with expertise in TypeScript, Node.js, React, and distributed systems engineering. Proven ability to design scalable microservices, optimize data pipelines, and deliver high-performance applications. Passionate about leveraging technology to build efficient systems and enhance user experiences in logistics and supply chain management.
  </summary>

  <education>
    <institution>
      <name>University of Louisiana at Monroe</name>
      <location>Monroe, LA</location>
      <degree>Bachelor of Science in Computer Science, Minor in Mathematics</degree>
      <gpa>4.0 / 4.0</gpa>
      <date>Aug 2022 – May 2026 (Senior)</date>
      <courses>
        <course>Data Structures</course>
        <course>Algorithms</course>
        <course>Object-Oriented Programming</course>
        <course>Database Management</course>
        <course>Operating Systems</course>
        <course>Computer Networks</course>
      </courses>
    </institution>
  </education>

  <experience>
    <job>
      <title>Software Engineering Intern (ML)</title>
      <company>Simons Foundation (SCC, Flatiron Institute)</company>
      <location>New York, NY</location>
      <date>July 2025 – Aug 2025</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Built a scalable, production-grade image processing pipeline to handle 1.2TB of cryo-EM and whole-slide images, collaborating with computational biologists to parallelize processing via SLURM job arrays, PyTorch + Triton kernels, and Ceph/S3 data access.</achievement>
        <achievement>Improved cellular classification model to a 0.91 macro F1-score by developing a spatio-temporal 3D-CNN over 4-channel inputs, in coordination with domain experts across 600+ timepoints and 25,000+ cells.</achievement>
        <achievement>Launched Chart-Gizmos, an open-source Python library for browser-based scientific visualizations, integrating Chart.js into H5Gizmos with a modular API and full documentation.</achievement>
        <achievement>Orchestrated a distributed inference pipeline for millions of nucleus state predictions, achieving a 22x speedup (45 min to 2 min) on a 10-GPU cluster through optimized batching and mixed-precision.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
    <job>
      <title>Software Engineer</title>
      <company>University of Louisiana - Monroe</company>
      <location>Monroe, LA</location>
      <date>Jan 2023 – Present</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Integrated Microsoft Teams API with Drupal CMS via OAuth 2.0, reducing administrative overhead from 4 hours to 30 minutes weekly.</achievement>
        <achievement>Engineered a Python/MySQL/ETL pipeline to migrate 10,000+ legacy records into Drupal 10, accelerating query performance by 15% and reducing storage costs by 10%.</achievement>
        <achievement>Automated end-to-end testing for 50+ webpages using Selenium and Cypress, boosting pre-deployment issue detection by 75% within the CI/CD pipeline.</achievement>
        <achievement>Redesigned the web presence for the Museum of Natural History and Alumni departments, resulting in a 25% increase in average session duration.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
    <job>
      <title>Teaching Assistant</title>
      <company>University of Louisiana - Monroe</company>
      <location>Monroe, LA</location>
      <date>Aug 2024 – Dec 2024</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Mentored 40+ students in Java, focusing on object-oriented programming and data structures, improving average course grades by 20%.</achievement>
        <achievement>Collaborated with professors to develop targeted instruction strategies that enhanced classroom performance.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
    <job>
      <title>Software Developer</title>
      <company>Clamphook - EdTech</company>
      <location>Lalitpur, NP</location>
      <date>Oct 2022 – May 2023</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Spearheaded a FastAPI and React-based CBT platform with Redis caching and Nginx load balancing, enabling 5,000+ concurrent users and supporting 5x enrollment growth.</achievement>
        <achievement>Architected a Docker-based microservices infrastructure and automated CI/CD pipelines, achieving 99.9% uptime for a Next.js web app and a React Native iOS app with 5,000+ downloads.</achievement>
        <achievement>Pioneered a real-time analytics dashboard with gamification features, using Flask-SocketIO and Chart.js to drive an 8% increase in user engagement.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
    <job>
      <title>EPCM Content Creator</title>
      <company>Clamphook</company>
      <location>Kathmandu, NP</location>
      <date>May 2021 – Nov 2022</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Authored 500+ exam-focused MCQs and comprehensive study materials using LaTeX, adopted by 1,000+ students.</achievement>
        <achievement>Increased course enrollment by 30% year-over-year through targeted marketing and engaging visual content created with Adobe Suite.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
    <job>
      <title>Frontend Developer</title>
      <company>Padhao Academy</company>
      <location>Remote</location>
      <date>Oct 2021 – Dec 2021</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Implemented JWT-based authentication with role-based access control, achieving 100% GDPR compliance for 5,000+ users.</achievement>
        <achievement>Developed a responsive frontend using Next.js, TypeScript, and Tailwind CSS, improving page load speed by 35%.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
    <job>
      <title>Technical Support Staff</title>
      <company>BABA COMPUTER POKHARA</company>
      <location>Pokhara, NP</location>
      <date>Jan 2022 – Mar 2022</date>
      <achievements>
        <achievement>Diagnosed and resolved hardware/software issues across Windows, Linux, and MacOS, reducing system downtime by 40% for 200+ students.</achievement>
        <achievement>Built 20+ high-performance PCs and deployed Wi-Fi networks and CCTV systems across 10+ client sites.</achievement>
      </achievements>
    </job>
  </experience>

  <research>
    <focus>Implementation of Meissel-Lehmer Method for Prime Counting: Applying advanced algorithmic approaches to solve complex mathematical problems in number theory.</focus>
    <focus>Nucleus Fate Classification in Early-Stage Embryo: Utilizing computer vision and deep learning models to classify and predict cellular development in embryonic stages.</focus>
    <focus>Code Stroke Research and Training: Developing and evaluating technology-driven training solutions to improve response times and outcomes for stroke patients.</focus>
  </research>

  <projects>
    <project>
      <name>NoteMeet</name>
      <link>https://notemeet.dineshchhantyal.com</link>
      <description>Architected an AI-powered meeting assistant that automates meeting joining, recording, summarization, and action extraction. Implemented a Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) system with LangChain and OpenAI GPT. Built on a highly scalable, event-driven AWS Infrastructure (Lambda, S3, DynamoDB) and integrated with Google Meet API.</description>
      <accomplishments>
        <accomplishment>Achieved 95% transcription accuracy, reducing manual correction time by 80%, and increased user productivity by 40% through automated action item extraction.</accomplishment>
      </accomplishments>
      <technologies>Next.js, React, Node.js, Express, PostgreSQL, Prisma ORM, TypeScript, Redux, Tailwind CSS, Auth.js v5, OAuth 2.0, JWT, Twilio Authy, Resend, AWS (S3, Lambda, EventBridge, Transcribe, Elemental MediaConvert, SageMaker), DynamoDB, Terraform, Socket.IO, Apollo Server, Redis, Selenium, Assembly AI, OpenAI API.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>RhymeAI</name>
      <link>https://rhyme-ai.vercel.app</link>
      <description>Pioneered a multi-agent AI Emcee platform using Next.js and TypeScript that automates live event hosting by generating narratives, scripts, and studio-grade multilingual voice-overs. Orchestrated specialized AI agents using Gemini 2.5 Pro API, LangChain, ElevenLabs TTS API, and Veo.</description>
      <accomplishments>
        <accomplishment>Delivered a flawless, human-like emcee performance, enhancing audience engagement and operational efficiency for live events.</accomplishment>
      </accomplishments>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>OfferMart</name>
      <link>https://offermart.vercel.app</link>
      <description>Engineered a supply chain optimization marketplace using Next.js, Node.js, and MongoDB to combat food waste. Implemented role-based access control (RBAC) and an AI-driven verification system powered by TensorFlow.js for real-time product condition analysis.</description>
      <accomplishments>
        <accomplishment>Contributed to a 25% reduction in food waste for partner vendors and increased user conversion by 30% with an AI-powered dynamic pricing model.</accomplishment>
      </accomplishments>
      <technologies>Next.js, React, Node.js/Express, TypeScript, Python, PostgreSQL, AWS S3, Stripe API, OpenAI DALL-E, Deepseek, Serverless Functions (Vercel), REST API.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>ULM Pharmacy - Code Stroke Pro Website</name>
      <link>https://codestrokepro.org/</link>
      <description>Developed and launched a comprehensive informational website for the ULM Pharmacy Department's 'Code Stroke Pro' initiative, serving as a central hub for training, resources, and clinical protocols.</description>
      <accomplishments>
        <accomplishment>Designed a user-friendly interface that improved access to critical stroke response protocols and educational materials for medical professionals. The fully responsive site increased accessibility by 40% for on-the-go medical staff using mobile devices.</accomplishment>
      </accomplishments>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>TimeClock</name>
      <link>https://github.com/dineshchhantyal/TimeClock</link>
      <description>Engineered a TypeScript-based real-time workforce management platform using React, Node.js, and PostgreSQL. Implemented live time monitoring with Socket.io, automated timesheets, and manager dashboards.</description>
      <accomplishments>
        <accomplishment>Reduced administrative overhead by 40% and improved billing accuracy for enterprise clients through RESTful API integration with payroll systems.</accomplishment>
      </accomplishments>
      <technologies>Next.js 14, TypeScript, Node.js/Express, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Prisma ORM, React, Tailwind CSS, Auth.js v5, Server Actions, Resend.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Automated Resume &amp; Cover Letter Generator</name>
      <description>A Python-based tool to streamline the job application process by generating customized application documents.</description>
      <technologies>Python, Automation.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Content Creator Agent</name>
      <description>An AI assistant for generating blog posts and marketing copy. Reduced content creation time by 60% with OpenAI API integration and improved content relevance by 50% with a prompt-tuning interface.</description>
      <technologies>Next.js, TypeScript, Node.js, OpenAI API, Vercel AI SDK, Tailwind CSS.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Clamphook Academy</name>
      <description>A comprehensive e-learning platform featuring secure payments, live classes via Zoom SDK, and cross-platform access with a Flutter application.</description>
      <technologies>Next.js, TypeScript, Payment Gateway, Redux, JWT, ZoomSDK, Vercel, Flutter.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>CheerPal</name>
      <description>Led a team of 6 to develop a reminder app with Firebase Cloud Messaging and an ML-powered recommendation engine that improved product click-through rates by 40%.</description>
      <technologies>Next.js, Flutter, TypeScript, Firebase Cloud Messaging, Machine Learning.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Placeaway / Trip Planner</name>
      <description>Developed a rental and trip-planning platform that reduced estimated travel time for users by 20% by implementing Dijkstra's algorithm for route optimization.</description>
      <technologies>React, TypeScript, Node.js/Express, MongoDB, Redux, Google Maps API, Vercel.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>3D-CNN Classification / FEM Simulation</name>
      <description>Trained a 3D-CNN model achieving 92% accuracy on medical imaging datasets and developed visualizations that led to a 50% faster analysis of airfoil performance.</description>
      <technologies>Python, TensorFlow/Keras, NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Movie Flower Garden Visualization</name>
      <description>An interactive data visualization representing movie data as flowers. Increased user engagement time by over 200% compared to traditional tables.</description>
      <technologies>D3.js, JavaScript, SVG, IMDb Dataset.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Rookie Discord Bot</name>
      <description>Created a bot to manage class schedules during the pandemic, increasing schedule adherence by 50% and homework submissions by 30%.</description>
      <technologies>JavaScript, Node.js, Discord.js, MongoDB.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>COVID-19 Tracker</name>
      <description>A dashboard that fetched and displayed COVID-19 data, achieving 99.9% uptime on Firebase Hosting during peak traffic.</description>
      <technologies>React, Firebase Hosting, Material-UI, Chart.js, Leaflet.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>NEB Exam Poll</name>
      <description>A real-time polling application for student exams.</description>
      <technologies>React, Firebase, Firestore, Material UI.</technologies>
    </project>
    <project>
      <name>Amazon / Google Clones</name>
      <description>Demonstrated full-stack proficiency by building and deploying two complex, real-world applications from scratch, including secure authentication and payment integration.</description>
      <technologies>React.js, Next.js, Firebase, Stripe, GCP, Tailwind CSS.</technologies>
    </project>
  </projects>

  <skills>
    <skill_category name="Programming Languages">
      <skill>TypeScript</skill>
      <skill>JavaScript (ES6+)</skill>
      <skill>Python</skill>
      <skill>Node.js</skill>
      <skill>Java</skill>
      <skill>SQL</skill>
      <skill>Bash</skill>
      <skill>C</skill>
    </skill_category>
    <skill_category name="Frontend">
      <skill>React</skill>
      <skill>Next.js</skill>
      <skill>HTML5</skill>
      <skill>CSS3</skill>
      <skill>Sass</skill>
      <skill>Tailwind CSS</skill>
      <skill>Responsive Design</skill>
      <skill>Figma</skill>
      <skill>UX Collaboration</skill>
    </skill_category>
    <skill_category name="Backend">
      <skill>Node.js</skill>
      <skill>Express</skill>
      <skill>FastAPI</skill>
      <skill>Flask</skill>
      <skill>Django</skill>
      <skill>REST APIs</skill>
      <skill>GraphQL</skill>
      <skill>Microservices</skill>
      <skill>Serverless Architecture</skill>
    </skill_category>
    <skill_category name="Databases">
      <skill>MySQL</skill>
      <skill>PostgreSQL</skill>
      <skill>MongoDB</skill>
      <skill>Redis</skill>
      <skill>NoSQL</skill>
      <skill>Data Pipelines</skill>
      <skill>ETL</skill>
      <skill>Data Modeling</skill>
    </skill_category>
    <skill_category name="Cloud &amp; DevOps">
      <skill>AWS (Lambda, S3, EC2, DynamoDB)</skill>
      <skill>GCP</skill>
      <skill>Docker</skill>
      <skill>Kubernetes</skill>
      <skill>Terraform (IaC)</skill>
      <skill>NGINX</skill>
      <skill>CI/CD (GitHub Actions)</skill>
    </skill_category>
    <skill_category name="AI &amp; Machine Learning">
      <skill>Deep Learning</skill>
      <skill>PyTorch</skill>
      <skill>Hugging Face Transformers</skill>
      <skill>Scikit-learn</skill>
      <skill>Computer Vision</skill>
      <skill>MLflow</skill>
      <skill>LangChain</skill>
      <skill>RAG</skill>
    </skill_category>
    <skill_category name="Development Tools">
      <skill>Git</skill>
      <skill>GitHub</skill>
      <skill>Agile</skill>
      <skill>Scrum</skill>
      <skill>Documentation</skill>
      <skill>Code Review</skill>
      <skill>Open Source Contributions</skill>
      <skill>Testing (Selenium, Cypress)</skill>
    </skill_category>
  </skills>

  <leadership>
    <organization>
      <name>Google Developer Student Club, President</name>
      <date>Sep 2024 – Present</date>
      <description>Directed a team of 12 board members and 250+ club members to organize impactful events, including the ULM Hackathon, TechXpo, IT Code Challenge, and mentorship programs focused on Software, AI/ML, Cloud, InfoSec, and IoT.</description>
    </organization>
    <organization>
      <name>IEEE Shreveport Section, Webmaster</name>
      <date>Jan 2025 – Present</date>
    </organization>
    <organization>
      <name>ULM Student Affairs, Student Advisory Council</name>
      <date>Sep 2024 – Present</date>
      <description>Worked with students and staff to share ideas and improve campus life, focusing on fun activities, helping new students feel welcome, and making sure everyone’s opinions are heard during group meetings.</description>
    </organization>
    <organization>
      <name>Shree Malika Youth Club, Program Manager</name>
      <date>Sep 2018 – Present</date>
    </organization>
  </leadership>

  <awards>
    <award>
      <title>Student Advertising Competition: Best Marketing Material (Bronze)</title>
      <issuer>ULM Marketing Program</issuer>
      <date>May 2025</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>Student Advertising Competition: Best Video Award (Bronze)</title>
      <issuer>ULM Marketing Program</issuer>
      <date>May 2025</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>Outstanding Student Employee Award</title>
      <issuer>University of Louisiana Monroe</issuer>
      <date>Apr 2025</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>1st Place – Project Presentation at ULM Spring 2025 Career Fair</title>
      <issuer>AWS</issuer>
      <date>Mar 2025</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>2nd Place, BEE Integration Competition</title>
      <issuer>MAA (Louisiana-Mississippi Section)</issuer>
      <date>Feb 2025</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>ICPC NA South Division 2024 State Champion – Division 1</title>
      <issuer>ICPC</issuer>
      <date>Nov 2024</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>Opportunity Fund Award ($2,500 Grant for TechXpo ULM)</title>
      <issuer>Office of the President, ULM</issuer>
      <date>Nov 2024</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>1st Place - 90-Second Elevator Pitch Competition</title>
      <issuer>ULM Office of Career &amp; Student Development</issuer>
      <date>Oct 2024</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>2nd Place - ACM Coding Contest</title>
      <issuer>Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)</issuer>
      <date>Oct 2024</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>3rd Place, BEE Integration Competition</title>
      <issuer>MAA (Louisiana-Mississippi Section)</issuer>
      <date>Mar 2024</date>
    </award>
    <award>
      <title>Presidential List (4.0 GPA)</title>
      <issuer>University of Louisiana Monroe</issuer>
      <date>May 2022, Jan 2023, Dec 2023, Jun 2024</date>
    </award>
  </awards>

  <certifications>
    <certification>
      <title>Data Parallelism: How to Train Deep Learning Models on Multiple GPUs</title>
      <issuer>NVIDIA</issuer>
      <date>Issued Jul 2025</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Fundamentals of Deep Learning</title>
      <issuer>NVIDIA</issuer>
      <date>Issued Jul 2025</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Databricks Certified Generative AI Engineer Associate</title>
      <issuer>Databricks</issuer>
      <date>Issued May 2025</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Ethical Hacking Essentials</title>
      <issuer>EC Innovations, Inc.</issuer>
      <date>Issued Dec 2024</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Supervised Machine Learning: Classification</title>
      <issuer>IBM</issuer>
      <date>Issued Aug 2024</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Unsupervised Machine Learning</title>
      <issuer>IBM</issuer>
      <date>Issued Aug 2024</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Exploratory Data Analysis for Machine Learning</title>
      <issuer>IBM</issuer>
      <date>Issued Jul 2024</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Supervised Machine Learning: Regression</title>
      <issuer>IBM</issuer>
      <date>Issued Jul 2024</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Advanced Java Programming</title>
      <issuer>LinkedIn</issuer>
      <date>Issued Mar 2024</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>JavaScript I Certificate</title>
      <issuer>HackerRank</issuer>
      <date>Issued Dec 2022</date>
    </certification>
    <certification>
      <title>Problem Solving (Basic) Certificate</title>
      <issuer>HackerRank</issuer>
      <date>Issued Dec 2022</date>
    </certification>
  </certifications>

</resume>
